（ナレーション）＜西暦２１９９年＞
＜地球は
ガミラスとの戦いに敗れ→
滅びゆこうとしていた＞
＜人類滅亡まで　あと１年＞
＜宇宙戦艦ヤマトは　希望を求め→
１６万８０００光年のかなた
イスカンダルへ向け　旅立った＞
＜ヤマトは　途中
ガミラス冥王星前線基地を撃破＞
＜太陽系を離れ　ついに
外宇宙へと艦を進めていた＞
[外:6481AA074865672B97996C8989BEC66F]（百合亜）
今日の「ヤマトラジオ文学館」は→
Today, on Yamato Radio Theater,
someone calling themselves Shiro Shinta has requested
ラジオネーム
シロシンタさんのリクエストで→
２１世紀末の名作→
one of the famous late 21st century stories,
"The Heart of Observer #9."
「観測員９号の心」です。
[外:6481AA074865672B97996C8989BEC66F]（百合亜）
まだ　火星に　町がなかった頃→
Back when there were still no towns on Mars,
シレーヌス海のほとりに→
a single observation station stood alone, at the edge of Mare Sirenum.
ぽつんと
恒点観測所が建っていました。→
No one ever visited this forgotten tower,
訪れる人もなく→
忘れられたかのようにたたずむ
その塔に→
若い観測所員が一人→
where a single, young observer lived like a lighthouse keeper.
まるで　灯台守のように
暮らしていました。→
彼には名もなく　ただ
９号という数字だけが　身の証し。
He had no name, only the number 9 to mark his existence.
A Clockwork Parable
ピッピッピッピッ…（キーボード操作音）
（ＡＵ０９）ガミロイドＡカラＢへ
視覚センサー　移植。
Transferring visual sensors from Garmiroid A to Garmiroid B.
（ＡＵ０９）ガミロイドＡカラＢへ
視覚センサー　移植。
ウマクイッタ。
It worked.
All three Garmiroid soldiers we recovered on Enceladus
（真田）エンケラドゥスで捕獲した
ガミロイド兵ですが→
were automata with orthodox AIs.
３体とも
オーソドックスなＡＩを備えた→
オートマタでした。
（古代進）オートマタ？
Automata?
（森雪）自動人形ってことね。
Mechanical dolls, right?
（真田）単純なプログラムの
膨大な多重処理によって→
By running a massive number of simple programs in parallel,
it can perform complex actions just like humans do.
人間と同じような複雑な行動を
可能にしている。→
これは　我々が使う人工知能と→
They share the same fundamental architecture as our artificial intelligences.
基本的なアーキテクチャが同じだ。
（新見）ガミラスが
我々と同じ数学を用い→
So we know Garmillas uses the same mathematics
and understanding of physics that we do.
同じ物理学を理解する→
コミュニケーション可能な文明を
持つことが→
Their culture should be one we can communicate with.
はっきりしたわ。
When you encounter a foreign civilization in space, this is very important.
（真田）
宇宙で　異文明と遭遇したとき→
このことは　重要な意味を持つ。
特に　戦争になったときにはな。
Especially in times of war.
（沖田十三）同じルールの
将棋が指せるということだ。
It lets us play shogi by the same rules.
なるほど。
（島）ほかに→
I see.
Did we manage to salvage any other information?
サルベージできた情報はないんですか？
例えば　敵の位置とか。
Such as enemy positions?
カチッ（スイッチ音）
ザザ…　ザザー…（ノイズ）
例えば　敵の位置とか。
Well, two of their storage units were too badly damaged for repair.
うむ…
３体のうち　２体のストレージは→
カチッ（スイッチ音）
ザザ…　ザザー…（ノイズ）
うむ…
３体のうち　２体のストレージは→
破損がひどく　修復不可能だった。
残り１体は　生き残っていたが
データは→
The other's survived, but the data is only accessible from a Garmillas mainframe.
ガミラスのメインフレームを
通さないと　取り出せない。
なんだ　それじゃあ…。
But then...
（真田）だが　方法はある。
ん？
However, there is a way.
ガミロイドに　しゃべってもらうのさ。
Have the Garmiroid tell us.
（ＡＵ０９）
メインフレーム　修復完了。
Mainframe restored.
ガミロイドオルタナティブ　再起動。
ピッピッピッピッ…
Rebooting Garmiroid Alternative.
（ＡＵ０９）私ガ分カルカ？　私ハ→
Can you hear me?
I am Type AU09, the sub-frame of this ship.
タイプＡＵ０９。
コノ艦ノ　サブフレーム。→
「アナライザー」ト呼ンデホシイ。
Please call me Analyzer.
ピピッ
ア…　ア　ア…→
A... A-An... An-Analyzer?
アナ…　アナライザー。
君ハ
異星文明使役型アンドロイド→
You are a rebooted, alternative version of a foreign civilization's servant android.
再起動　オルタナティブ。
I know... I'll call you Alter!
ソウダ！　君ヲ　「オルタ」ト呼ボウ。
（オルタ）オ…　ル…　タ。
Alter...
（島）ワープ終了。
周辺宙域に　敵影なし。
Warp complete.
No enemies in immediate vicinity.
Sanada, I will return to analyzing Alter.
（ＡＵ０９）真田サン
オルタノ分析ニ　戻リマス。
（真田）そうしてくれ。
（ＡＵ０９）ハ～イ！
Go ahead.
Right!
Analyzer appears to be enjoying himself.
アナライザー　なんだか楽しそうね。
そりゃそうだろ。
I'm sure he is.
同じ　機械の話し相手が
できたんだからな。
He has another machine to talk to.
What is this?
（ＡＵ０９）コレハ　ナンダ？
（オルタ）猫。
A cat.
違ウ違ウ。　コレハ　犬ナノダ。
No, no. This is a dog.
犬ハ　哺乳類ダ。　哺乳類ハ　動物ダ。
Dogs are mammals.
Mammals are animals.
（オルタ）哺乳類…　動物…。
デハ　コレハ？
Mammal. Animal.
Then what is this?
犬。
ウ～ン…　コレハ　猫ナノダ。
A dog.
No, this is a cat.
（新見）あら　アナライザー。
機械同士で　ないしょ話？
Oh, Analyzer. Are you two machines having a secret chat?
（ＡＵ０９）
人聞キノ悪イ。　オルタニ→
Nothing of the sort.
I am teaching Alter to speak.
言葉ヲ　教エテイルトコロデス。
To speak, huh?
言葉をねぇ。
ＯＳが連携できたんだから→
You were able to link operating systems, so just import the dictionary data.
辞書データを　そのまま
インポートしちゃいなさいよ。
The names alone are not enough.
名前ダケデハ　ダメナノデス。
物事ノ概念ヲ　理解サセルニハ→
To understand a concept, large numbers of exchanges are required.
膨大ナ　ヤリ取リガ
必要ナノデス。　ソレニ…。
And...
そうでした。
これを　艦内ネットワークに→
That's true.
You can't connect it to the ship's network.
つなげるわけにはいかないわよね。
（新見）
やっぱり　調査が不十分だわ。→
I was right. We didn't investigate enough.
これじゃあ
移住可能かどうか分からない。
This doesn't tell me if we can colonize it.
Do Automata Dream of Electric Sheep?
One day, an old mechanical engineer named Houdin
[外:6481AA074865672B97996C8989BEC66F]（百合亜）ある日　観測所に→
ウーダンと名乗る　年老いた→
機械技師が
イブという名の少女を連れて→
appeared at the observatory with a girl named Eve.
現れました。→
The meeting was magical.
その出会いは　神秘的でした。→
歌声に誘われて　海辺へ行くと→
Following the sound of a song to the sea,
#9 saw a girl sitting on a rock, singing.
岩の上に腰掛けて歌う
少女の姿があったのです。
（オルタ）ダ…　誰？
"Wh-Who?"
[外:6481AA074865672B97996C8989BEC66F]（百合亜）彼女は
振り向いて　こう言いました。→
She turned and asked,
「あなたは　だぁれ？」。→
"Who are you?"
「こんな所で　何をしているの？」。
"What are you doing out here?"
I met a goddess yesterday.
（オルタ）昨日　女神ニ会イマシタ。
（ＡＵ０９）女神？
A goddess?
（オルタ）コノ艦ノ　女神デス。
The goddess of this ship.
Who might that be?
誰ノコトダロウ？
They asked, "Who are you?"
「オ前ハ　誰ダ？」ト問ワレマシタ。
私ハ　「オルタ」ト答エマシタガ→
And I replied, "I am Alter."
「名前ヲ　聞イテイルノデハナイ」
ト言ワレマシタ。
And they said, "I am not asking for your name."
森船務長ノコトダロウカ？
Operations Officer Mori, perhaps?
Or Miss Niimi?
ソレトモ　新見女史？　マサカナ。
No, that's impossible.
（オルタ）
アナタハ　答エラレマスカ？→
Can you answer it?
Who are you?
「オ前ハ　何者カ？」。
I am...
私ハ…。
ピー（受信音）
（篠原・通信）こちら篠原。→
This is Shinohara.
前方の空間航跡を調査。
安全を確認しました。
I'm investigating the spatial wake in front of us.
I've confirmed that it's safe.
（相原）了解。　篠原　山本両名→
Roger.
Shinohara and Yamamoto completing patrol and returning to ship.
哨戒任務を終え　帰投します。
うむ。　両名を収容した後→
When both have returned,
０２００に　ワープ航法へと移行。
≫シューン（ドアの音）
we will move to warp navigation at 0200.
了解。　着艦準備　願います。
Roger.
Prepare for docking.
Analyzer, give them a hand, okay?
アナライザー
サポート　よろしくね。
Roger.
了解。
ピッピッピッピッ…
（遠山）へっへ～　僕の勝ちなんだな。
（岩田）がくっ…。
I win.
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ビィー　ビィー（サイレン）
（岩田）おっ　戻ってきた。→
They're back.
行くぞ。
おお～　ひどいんだな！→
Let's go.
No fair! I had a straight flush!
ストレートフラッシュ
だったんだな！
（篠原）ナビ子ちゃ～ん
自動着艦誘導　お願いね～。
Navi, handle the automatic docking guidance for me.
（ＳＩＤ）
自動操縦に　切り替わりました。
Switching to automatic control.
サンキュー　ナビ子。　ん？
Thanks, Navi.
ああ～
今　こいつ　やばいって思ったろ？
Just now, you were thinking that I'm nuts, weren't you?
I was not.
（玲）思ってません。
名前　付けて　かわいがってやると→
Name them, take care of them, and they'll do good work for you.
いい仕事するのよ　こいつらも。
Exactly like anyone else.
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　左舷　ハッチ開け。
（岩田）よ～し　始めるぜ。
Open hatch, port side.
Okay, let's get started.
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　誘導員は　引き込み準備に入れ。
Guidance team, prepare to pull them in.
（岩田）オーライ！　オーライ！
Okay, okay!
ピッピッピッピッ…
ン？　オルタ？
Alter?
ん？
（岩田）ん？　遠山
制御パネルに　エラー出てないか？
Toyama, is there an error on the control panel?
（遠山）モニターが落ちてるんだな。
The monitor's down.
（岩田）なんだと…。
≪ドドーン！
What?
ピーピーピー！（警告音）
強制パージ！
（ＳＩＤ）パージします。
Force purge!
Purging-
（遠山）なんだな～!?
（岩田）遠山～！
What the heck?!
Toyama!
ぐっ！
Shinohara!
（玲）篠原君！
任せろ！
I'm on it!
（２人）あぁ…。
What's wrong with you?
（玲）冗談じゃないわ！
一体どういうつもりなの!?
What were you thinking?
（岩田）はあ　その…
何がなんだか　さっぱり…。
Um, well... I really don't know what happened.
システム上　クレーンは
プログラム制御になってるんだろ？
That crane's movements are controlled by a program, right?
そうなんだな。
でも　今日は　なぜか→
Yes, they are.
But for some reason, the system monitor went down today.
システムのモニターが
ダウンしていたんだな。
Normally, they should shut down automatically.
（岩田）本来なら
自動停止するはずなんです。
今まで　こんなこと一度も…。
（榎本）バカ野郎！→
This has never happened.
You morons!
Just because it's never happened before
今まで　なかったからといって
今日　絶対→
doesn't mean it won't happen today!
起こらないとはかぎらない。
なんのために　人間が→
Why do you think we have humans there to help the machines?
機械をフォローしているか考えろ！
（２人）はい！
Yes, sir.
二人とも　すまなかった。
このとおりだ。
I'm sorry, both of you.
Forgive us.
（篠原）あっ　いえ…
分かってもらえれば…。
No... I mean, you're taking it seriously...
なあ？
（玲）えっ？　ええ…。
Right?
Y-Yes.
ピッピッピッピッ…
Before the accident, you were talking to Alter via network, weren't you?
事故が起きる前に　回線を通じて→
オルタと会話をしていたな？
ハイ。
格納庫の情報を→
Yes.
There was a very minor delay in the process that feeds hangar information
メインフレームに
フィードバックするタスク処理に→
back to the mainframe.
僅かな遅延が見られる。
アームの誤作動も　それが原因だ。
That caused the arm malfunction.
申シ訳アリマセン。
オルタとの会話が→
I'm terribly sorry.
Your conversations with Alter may be stressing the system unexpectedly.
予想外の負荷を
与えているのかもしれん。
Should this keep happening, I'll have to reformat you.
ミスが続くようなら
お前を初期化しなければならない。
ソレハ…。
That would be...
適切ナ判断ダト思ワレマス。
...the correct decision.
しばらく
オルタの分析作業は中断だ。
We're done analyzing Alter for a while.
You're forbidden from coming here or speaking to Alter via network.
ここに来ることも　回線を通じて→
オルタと話すことも禁止だ。
We'll keep an eye on things for now.
そのうえで　様子を見る。　いいな？
Got it?
Yes, sir.
ハイ。
[外:6481AA074865672B97996C8989BEC66F]（百合亜）老人が
イブを　船に戻してしまうと→
The old man sent Eve back, on board the ship.
And the observer desired nothing more than to see her again.
観測員は　無性に
彼女に会いたくなりました。→
For the first time in his life, he understood loneliness.
彼は　生まれて初めて
寂しいという感情を→
知ったのです。→
彼は決心しました→
He decided to go and see Eve.
イブに会おうと。→
彼には
それが　自分が何者かを知る→
He felt that this was the only way to learn who he was.
唯一の手だてだと思えたのです。
パリーン！（ガラスが割れる音）
I, Robot
（ＡＵ０９）
真田サン　オルタト話シテ→
Sanada, I learned something from talking with Alter.
分カッタコトガアリマス。
ん？
彼ラト私ハ　同ジ存在デス。
そうか。
They are just like me.
I see.
（ＡＵ０９）オルタニ
「オ前ハ何者カ？」ト聞カレマシタ。
Alter asked me who I am.
（真田）なんと答えた？
What did you tell him?
（ＡＵ０９）「友達」ト。
A friend.
（真田）友達か…。　いい答えだ。
A friend, huh?
Good answer.
Where is the goddess?
女神…　ドコ？
（百合亜）ん？
バチバチッ！
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ビー！　ビー！　ビー！（警報）
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ビー！　ビー！
ドウシタノデショウ？
What has happened?
Apparently, the lock to the analysis room has been destroyed.
解析室のロックが
破壊されたようです。
That Garmiroid...
例のガミロイド兵か。
保安部を急行させろ。
Send security at once!
Weapons approved, where appropriate!
（伊東）各自　状況判断のうえ
武器の使用を許可する。
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）艦内　第一種警戒態勢。→
Ship has moved to Alert Status 1.
繰り返す。
艦内　第一種警戒態勢。→
Repeat: Ship has moved to Alert Status 1.
The Garmiroid we recovered has escaped the analysis room.
鹵獲したガミロイド兵が
解析室より逃走した。→
当該目標は　現在も　艦内に潜伏中。
保安部員は　これを確保…。
It is hiding somewhere aboard the ship.
Security teams are to capture or destroy it.
（保安部員）ん？
（保安部員）あれか!?→
Is that it?
Repeat: Security teams are to capture or destroy it.
Stop!
止まれ！
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）保安部員はこれを確保→
もしくは　排除に当たれ。
（保安部員）動くなよ。→
Don't move. Stay right there.
じっとしてろ。
ピピッ　ピピッ
ピコン　ピコン　ピコン
目標発見！
左舷　第三デッキを逃走中。
Target acquired!
It's fleeing on the port side deck 3!
（ＡＵ０９）オルタハ　自分ガ
何者カ　知リタガッテイマシタ。
Alter wanted to know who he was.
女神ニ会エバ
ソノ答エガ分カルト→
He must think if he finds the goddess, he will learn.
思ッテイルノデショウ。
女神だって？
The goddess?
（ＡＵ０９）オルタハ　コノ艦ノ
女神ダト言ッテイマシタ。→
Alter said she was the goddess of this ship.
ソレト　モウヒトツ
ガミロイド兵ニツイテ→
And I learned one other important thing about the Garmiroids...
重要ナコトガ分カリマシタ。
（星名）
逃がすな！　隔壁　閉鎖しろ！
Don't let him escape. Seal the bulkheads.
Don't move!
（星名）動くな！　あっ！
≫ダダダッ！（銃声）
（伊東）ちっ！
森　ガミロイド兵の位置は？
Mori, where is the Garmiroid soldier?
第二デッキ　通風孔を
まっすぐ艦首に向かっています。
Heading straight toward the ship's bow, via the deck 2 ducts.
（星名）
この先は　開かずの間…　ですね。
We're heading toward the sealed room, aren't we?
（伊東）あそこには　イスカンダルまでの
自動航法装置がある。→
It contains the automatic guidance systems to take us to Iscandar.
ヤツの狙いは　それか？
（星名）いました！
Is that his objective?
There he is!
（伊東）ヤツを行かせるな！
破壊してかまわん！
Don't let him reach it! Destroy him if you must!
ダダダッ！　ダダダッ！
ピコン　ピコン
Enemy...
敵…　恐怖…→
Terror...
存在…　女神！
Being...
Goddess!
ピーン
ガミロイドは
第二砲塔　装備室に入りました。
The Garmiroid has entered the second turret loading room.
Flow My Tears, the Automata Said
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ビー！　ビー！　ビー！
（伊東）どうだ？
（星名）ダメです。　内側から→
Well?
No good. It's locked from the inside.
ロックが。
艦橋　ロックを解除してくれ。
Bridge, get that lock open!
開いたら　一斉に撃つ。
（相原・通信）艦橋です。
As soon as it opens, we fire.
This is the bridge.
He's infiltrated our security and locked it from the inside.
（相原）セキュリティーに侵入して
中から　ロックされました。→
こちらから解除するには
時間がかかります。
It will take some time to unlock it.
ちっ！
（ＡＵ０９）待ッテクダサイ。
Please stand by.
（伊東）ちょうどいい　ＡＵ０９。
ドアを開けろ。
Perfect timing, AU09. Open the door.
ソノ前ニ　銃ヲ収メテクダサイ。
Before that, put your guns away.
What?
（伊東）なんだって？
我々ガ　敵ダト思ワレタクナイ。
I don't want him to think we're enemies.
What are you talking about? Of course we're enemies.
（伊東）何言ってるんだ。
敵に決まってるじゃないか。
（百合亜）無抵抗の捕虜を殺す気？
Will you kill an unresisting prisoner?
（星名）岬君。
（伊東）捕虜だって？→
Misaki?
A prisoner?
バカバカしい。
あれは　ただの機械じゃないか。
That's stupid.
It's just a robot.
心があれば
機械も　捕虜として扱うべきよ。
If it has a heart, even a machine should be treated as a prisoner.
（伊東）心？　あれに心が？
A heart? It has a heart?
I was told it was an automaton.
（星名）あれは　自動人形だと→
副長ご自身がおっしゃったと
聞いていますが。
That's what the XO said.
It's true that the Garmiroids
確かに
ガミロイドは　プログラムの→
are automata that function by running massive numbers of programs.
膨大な積み重ねによって動く
自動人形だ。
でしょう？　所詮　機械は機械だ。
Correct? Machines are just machines.
But we cannot say for certain that our brains
（真田）だが　我々の脳も　同様に→
are not also automata that function via parallel processing.
多文書多重処理による
オートマタでないとは→
言い切れない。→
It seems you want to believe that
彼らの処理系に
我々と同種の意識は　芽生えない→
their processing circuitry cannot give rise to a consciousness like ours.
そう　君は思いたいようだ。　だが→
However, you cannot actually prove that that's the case.
それを証明することは→
実は　できないんだよ。
ふっ。　面白いお話ですね。
An interesting story.
I've retaken control of the security.
セキュリティー　奪イ返シマシタ。
Anyway, for the moment, put away your weapons.
とにかく
ここは　一旦　銃を収めてくれ。
（伊東）
副長が　そうおっしゃるなら。
If you say so, XO.
The door will open.
ドアガ開キマス。
≪ピーン
ちっ！
（百合亜）んん…。
（星名）岬君！
Misaki?
真田サン
速ヤカニ　オルタノ活動ヲ→
Sanada, I recommend that Alter be shut down immediately.
停止サセルコトヲ　進言シマス。
（伊東）どういうことだ？
Why is that?
Alter may commit suicide.
オルタは　自殺するかもしれない。
He is programmed to self-destruct if isolated and surrounded by enemies.
彼ハ　敵ニ囲マレ
孤立シタ状況ガ　続イタ場合→
自爆スルヨウニ
プログラム　サレテイルノデス。
Stop him!
（伊東）追え！　ヤツを食い止めろ！
はっ！
Analyzer, let's go.
（真田）アナライザー　行くぞ。
真田副長。
XO Sanada.
まさか　あなた　あれに
心があると思っていませんか？
You don't think it has a heart, do you?
（真田）私には
君に　心があるのかどうかさえ→
To me, it remains unclear whether even you have a heart.
分からない。
（伊東）んん…。
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ファン　ファン　ファン…（警報）
It may be that you don't have a heart like I do.
（真田）君には
私の中にあるような意識はなく→
You could just be simulating a human.
人間らしく振る舞っているだけ
なのかもしれない。
The Garmiroid soldier has exited the ship.
ガミロイド兵　船外に出ました。
It's moving along the upper deck, toward the bridge.
現在　上部甲板を
艦首に向かって移動中。
Don't allow it to get near the automatic guidance system.
ガミロイド兵を
自動航法装置に近づけるな。
破壊もやむをえん。
We will destroy it if we must.
Shell block destroyed.
シェルブロック破壊。
カーネルニ侵入。
Infiltrating kernel.
Dog.
（オルタ）犬…　猫…→
Cat.
存在…　女神…　死…。→
Being.
Goddess.
Death.
Fr... ie... n... d...
ト…　モ…　ダ…　チ…。
ピィーーー
Garmiroid Alternative has been shut down.
ガミロイドオルタナティブ
活動停止。
Mainframe has been reformatted and cannot be rebooted.
メインフレーム初期化。
再起動　不能デス。
（真田・通信）
タスクレコードを回収しろ。
Recover its task log.
Roger.
了解。
（真田）分析の結果が出た。→
The analysis is complete.
We found nothing in Alter's task log to indicate an activated booby trap.
オルタの
タスクレコードの中には→
ブービートラップが発動した形跡は
見つからなかった。
Then...
（ＡＵ０９）ソレデハ…。
うむ…。
Yes.
（真田）少なくとも　１人以上は→
If nothing else, he believed he still had at least one friend on this ship.
この艦に味方がいると
認識していたということだ。
≫シューン　シューン
The Heart of Observer #9
Eve's skin was peeled away, her joints torn off,
[外:6481AA074865672B97996C8989BEC66F]（百合亜）
イブの皮は剥がれ　関節はもげ→
revealing a body of gears and silicon.
歯車とシリコンで出来た→
機械の体が
あらわになりました。→
シレーヌスの海に沈んでいく
イブの姿を→
From the tower's window, #9 watched her sink into the Mare Sirenum.
９号は　塔の窓から見ていました。
"I no longer feel pity for that doll.
[外:6481AA074865672B97996C8989BEC66F]（百合亜）あの人形を　今はもう→
哀れだとは思っていません。→
自分もまた
ウーダン老人の作った→
Because I know that I am also one, created by Houdin,"
自動人形だと知ったのだから。
たった一人残された
観測所の小部屋で→
he thought to himself, alone in his small room in the observation station.
彼は思いました。→
[外:6481AA074865672B97996C8989BEC66F]　あの美しい人形に
心があったとしても→
Whether that beautiful doll did or did not have a heart,
また　なかったとしても→
it didn't matter to him.
自分には
関係のないことなのだと。→
And he thought this, as well...
そして　こうも思いました。→
"The fact that I have a heart
私の心が　このようにあることは→
is a secret that belongs only to me."
私だけの秘密なのだから。
Episode 9: Clockwork Prisoner
The Yamato plunges through a dimensional gap, into a ship's graveyard.
A cruel space, devoid of life.
And there, the shadow of an enemy ship appears.
Will they work together or against one other?
Will men be able to work together, rather than wait for death?
Next time: Graveyard of the Universe.
There are 325 days left before humanity is extinct.
アフリカ開発会議が２日目を迎え
安倍総理は、アフリカでテロが続
く地域の安定のために、
５年間で１０００億円の支援を行
うことを表明した。
中継。